Register of the Albert Glotzer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Social Democratic Period Papers, 1958-1999
  - Subject file
    - Labor--United States
      - Miscellaneous, 1960-1996 (Folder 63: 9)
        Printed matter and circulated documents. Includes issuances of the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, the Office Employees International Union, and the United Automobile Workers Union
    - LaRouche, Lyndon, circa 1975-1988 (Folder 64: 1)
      Printed matter
    - Latin America, 1968-1994 (Folder 64: 2)
      Printed matter and circulated documents, 1968-1994, mainly about Central America and Cuba. Includes Comandante Bayardo Arce's Secret Speech before the Nicaraguan Socialist Party (PSN)
    - League for Industrial Democracy, 1965-1993 (Folder 64: 3)
      Printed matter and circulated documents. Includes The Roots of the Dominican Crisis by Theodore Draper; On the Nature of Communism and Relations with Communists by Irving Howe; Labor and the Liberal Tradition by Lane Kirkland; The Evolving Threat of the New Right by Arch Puddington; The Ideology of Union Busting by Steve Lagerfeld; A Hidden Agenda: The National Right to Work Committee and Its Campaign to Undermine American Trade Unions by Karin Chenoweth
    - Marxism and political ideology, 1959-1983 (Folder 64: 4)
      Essays and printed matter, 1959-1983. Includes "Mysticism and Political Thought: A Critical Essay" by B. Paul Meinhardt; "Economic Growth, Poverty, and the International Agencies" by Walter Galenson
    - Middle East, 1971-1997 (Folder 64: 5)
      Printed articles, serial issues, and flyers. Includes issuances of the American Zionist Movement and the Youth Institute for Peace in the Middle East; "Lebanon: Israel's Gift to America" by Steven C. Munson
    - New Chelsea Reform Democratic Club (New York City), 1963-1974, undated
      Correspondence, reports, circular letters, membership lists, election campaign literature, leaflets, and flyers
      - 1963-1965 (Folder 64: 6)
      - 1966 (Folder 64: 7)
      - 1967-1974 (Folder 64: 8)
      - Undated (Folder 64: 9)
    - Old Timers (Organization), 1976-1980 (Folder 64: 10)
      Circular letters and programs
    - Peace movements and disarmament, 1961-1985 (Folder 64: 11)
      Printed matter and circulated documents. Includes newsletter of the Committee of Correspondence (A. J. Muste organization)
    - Pumpkin Papers Irregulars, 1981-1989 (Folder 65: 1)
      Circular letters and issues of The Warbler
    - Rizzi, Brunoe, 1985 (Folder 65: 2)
      Printed article
    - Serge, Victor, 1982 (Folder 65: 3)
      "The Last Years of Victor Serge, 1941-1947" by Julian Gorkin; "Victor Serge and Leon Trotsky: Relations 1936-1940" by Richard Greeman
    - Shorthand reporting, 1958-1971 (Folder 65: 4)
      Correspondence, constitutions, printed matter, and circulated documents, 1958-1971, relating mainly to the Federation of Shorthand Reporters and the New York State Shorthand Reporters Association
    - Socialism--United States, 1976-1996 (Folder 65: 5)
      Printed matter and reports. Includes material on Socialist Scholars Conferences, and reports on the Socialist Party, U.S.A. (Frank Zeidler/David McReynolds group)
    - Souvarine, Boris, 1984 (Folder 65: 6)
      Obituary
    - Soviet Union, 1964-1991 (Folder 65: 7)
      Printed matter and circulated documents, 1964-1991, mainly relating to Soviet dissidents and Soviet Jews. Includes material on the Conference on the Nature of the Soviet Union and Its Role in the World Today (1979)
    - Stolar (Abe) case, 1975-1989, undated
      Correspondence, petitions, resolutions, circulated documents, and press coverage, relating to efforts to secure permission from the Soviet government for Abe Stolar, an American who had immigrated to the Soviet Union in the 1930s, to leave the country with his family
      - 1975-1980 (Folder 65: 8)
      - 1981-1989, undated (Folder 65: 9)
    - Trotsky, Leon, and Trotskyism
      - General, 1980-1995 (Folder 65: 10)
        Printed matter and circulated documents. Includes obituary of Erwin Ackerknecht
      - BBC television broadcast on 100th anniversary of Trotsky's birth, 1976 (Folder 65: 11)
      - Committee for the Study of Leon Trotsky's Legacy, 1994-1998 (Folder 65: 12)
        Printed articles and circular letters.
      - France, 1967, 1994 (Folder 66: 1)
        Report on Voix Ouvrière, 1967; obituaries of Raymond Molinier, 1994
      - Great Britain, 1975-1990
        - Correspondence and reports, 1976-1987 (Folder 66: 2)
          Relating to Gerry Healy and the Workers Revolutionary Party. Includes correspondence with Jock Haston, David North, Harold Robins and George L. Weissman; "A Statement on the Slanders Circulated by the Healy Group against Hansen, Novack, and the Socialist Workers Party"; report of the International Committee of the Fourth International; "Hamlet without the Prince" and "Archie Rice and the Marxist Party" by Ted Crawford
        - Printed matter, including serial issues, printed articles, clippings, and flyers, 1975-1990 (Folder 66: 3)
          Relating to Gerry Healy and the Workers Revolutionary Party and to the Militant group
      - Russian interpretations, 1988-1994 (Folder 66: 4)
        Printed matter and writings. Includes articles from the Russian press; "The Origins of the Stalinist Bureaucracy: Some New Historical Facts" by Alexander Podsheldolkin; open letter to Dmitri Volkogonov by Pierre Broué and Aleksandr Pantsov
      - United States
        - General, 1964-1965, 1976-1977, 1984, 1990 (Folder 66: 5)
          Serial issues, printed articles, clippings, and flyers, 1964-1990. Includes: Spartacist no. 1 (1964), no. 4 (1965); Socialist Voice no. 2 (1976-1977); Socialist Action Information Bulletin vol. 1 no. 1 (1984); photocopy of Socialist Workers Party letter terminating relations with the Fourth International (1990)
        - Individuals, 1980-1997 (Folder 66: 6)
          Printed matter and circulated documents, relating to specific American Trotskyists or former Trotskyists. Includes obituaries of or articles about Raya Dunayevskaya, Joseph Giganti, Frank Glass, Bessie Spiegel Gogol, Francis Heisler, James Kutcher, Alfred M. Loewenthal, Howard Mayhew, Harry Milton, Thomas J. O'Flaherty, Myra Tanner Weiss, and Milton Zaslow; inventory of papers of Martin Abern
        - Bulletin in Defense of Marxism (publication of Fourth Internationalist Tendency), 1983-1986, 1989, 1991
          - 1983. No. 1 (Folder 66: 7)
          - 1984. No. 2-8 (Folder 66: 8)
          - 1984. No. 9-14 (Folder 66: 9)
          - 1985. No. 15-25 (Folder 66: 10)
          - 1986. No. 26-30, 34, 36 (Folder 67: 1)
          - 1989. No. 59 (Folder 67: 2)
          - 1991. No. 82 (Folder 67: 3)
    - Trotsky (Leon) family, 1935, 1982, 1989-1995
      - General, 1982, 1990 (Folder 67: 4)
        Genealogical charts and data by Pierre Broué; clipping, 1982; "The Tragedy of the Bronstein Family" by Alain Brossat, 1990
      - Akselrod, Yulia (granddaughter of Leon Trotsky), 1989-1995 (Folder 67: 5-6)
        Photocopies of memoirs with related correspondence
      - Sedov, Sergei (son of Leon Trotsky), 1935 (Folder 67: 7)
        Photocopy of translated and edited version of 1935 letters to his wife from Soviet prison camp
    - United States politics and foreign policy, 1966-1992 (Folder 67: 8)
      Printed matter and circulated documents. Includes "Government-Funded Activism: Hiding behind the Public Interest" by H. Peter Metzger; issuances of the New York Coalition of Center Democrats
    - Miscellany, 1961-1996 (Folder 67: 9)
- Photographs, 1927-1953 (Box Photo file 91006)
  - 13 prints of Leon Trotsky, 1930s (Folder A)
  - 4 prints of Leon Trotsky with others, including his wife, daughter, son Lev Sedov, Charles Curtiss, and Abraham and Roman Sobolevicius, 1930s (Folder B)
  - 6 prints of Leon Trotsky and Albert Glotzer and the Trotsky residence in Kadikoy, Turkey, 1931 (Folder C)
  - 35 prints of Leon Trotsky, Albert Glotzer and others at hearings of the Dewey Commission, Mexico City, 1937 (Folder D)
    Persons depicted include Carleton Beals, John Dewey, James T. Farrell, Jan Frankel, Albert Goldman, Frida Kahlo, Pearl Kluger, Suzanne La Follette, John McDonald, George Novack, Diego Rivers, Otto Rühle, Herbert Solow, Benjamin Stolberg, Natalia Sedova, Jean Van Heijenoort, and Bernard Wolfe
  - 7 prints, including three relating to the Leon Trotsky assassination, one of Trotsky's grave, one of the Trotsky museum, and one of Diego Rivera murals depicting Trotsky and other communist leaders (Folder E)
  - 4 prints, including one of Albert Glotzer with Gil Green, Max Shachtman and others, 1927; one of Walter Held, circa 1934; one of James P. Cannon and Max Shachtman, 1938; and one of Albert Glotzer with Natalia Sedova, 1953 (Folder F)